Alexander Hamilton
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Papers of Alexander Hamilton 1708-1903 (bulk 1777-1804)
MSS24612
Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804
12,000 items 44 containers plus 3 oversize 22.4 linear feet 34 microfilm reels
Manuscript Division Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Correspondence, speeches and writings, legal and financial papers, printed matter, and other papers, chiefly from 1777 to 1804. Includes material relating to Alexander Hamilton's personal life and public career, especially his service as an aide to George Washington during the Revolutionary War, his participation in the United States Continental Congress and the Constitutional Convention, his service as United States secretary of the treasury, his New York law practice, and his service as inspector general of the army.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the Library's online catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically therein.
Names:
Hamilton, Alexander, 1757-1804; Adams, John, 1735-1826 --Correspondence; Church, Angelica Schuyler, 1756-1815--Correspondence; Church family; Clay, Henry, 1777-1852--Correspondence; Hamilton, Elizabeth Schuyler, 1757-1854--Correspondence; Hamilton family; Hamtramck, John Francis, 1756-1803--Correspondence; Heth, William, 1735-1808--Correspondence; Jay, John, 1745-1829--Correspondence; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826--Correspondence; King, Rufus, 1755-1827--Correspondence; Lafayette, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert du Motier, marquis de, 1757-1834--Correspondence; Lee, Henry, 1756-1818--Correspondence; L'Enfant, Pierre Charles, 1754-1825--Correspondence; McHenry, James, 1753-1816--Correspondence; McLean family; Monroe, James, 1758-1831--Correspondence; Morris, Robert, 1734-1806--Correspondence; Pickering, Timothy, 1745-1829--Correspondence; Pinckney, Charles Cotesworth, 1746-1825--Correspondence; Rice, Nathan, 1754-1829--Correspondence; Rivardi, John J. U. (John Jacob Ulrich)--Correspondence; Schuyler, Philip John, 1733-1804--Correspondence; Schuyler family; Sedgwick, Theodore, 1746-1813--Correspondence; Seton, William, 1746-1798--Correspondence; Smith, William Stephens, 1755-1816--Correspondence; Steuben, Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Gerhard Augustin, Baron von, 1730-1794--Correspondence; Swan, Caleb, d. 1809--Correspondence; Tousard, Louis de, 1749-1817--Correspondence; Troup, Robert, 1757-1832--Correspondence; Wadsworth, Jeremiah, 1743-1804--Correspondence; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Correspondence; Wilkinson, James, 1757-1825--Correspondence; Wolcott, Oliver, 1760-1833--Correspondence; Mint of the United States; New York (State). Supreme Court; United States. Army. Office of the Inspector General; United States. Constitutional Convention (1787); United States. Continental Congress; United States. Dept. of the Treasury; Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures; First Church of Albany. Records of the First Church of Albany (1780)
Subjects:
Finance, Public--United States; Manufacturing industries--United States; National banks (United States); Practice of law--New York (State)--New York; France--Foreign relations--United States; Great Britain--Foreign relations--United States; United States--Economic conditions--To 1865; United States--Foreign relations--France; United States--Foreign relations--Great Britain; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783
Occupations:
Army officers; Cabinet officers; Delegates, U.S. Continental Congress--New York (State); Lawyers; Public officials; Statesmen
Administrative Information
Provenance:
The papers of Alexander Hamilton (1757-1804), attorney, secretary of the treasury, and inspector general of the army, were acquired by the Library in several installments between 1904 and 1997. The largest and initial acquisition was transferred from the State Department by executive order in 1904. In 1916 Hamilton's legal papers were purchased and a collection of his personal papers was received as the gift of Allan McLane Hamilton. A supplementary group of legal papers and letters was transferred from the Treasury Department in 1917. In 1942 a deposit made in 1930 by Alexander Hamilton and Pierpont M. Hamilton was converted into a gift, and another deposit made in 1939 by Mrs. John C. Bartholf was purchased in 1958. Smaller acquisitions have been added periodically to the papers by purchase or gift.
Microfilm:
A microfilm edition of part of these papers is available on thirty-four reels. This edition, made in 1981, replaces a forty-six reel edition created in 1965. Consult a reference librarian in the Manuscript Division concerning availability for purchase or interlibrary loan.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1757, Jan. 11 Born, Charlestown, Nevis, Leeward Islands, British West Indies
1766-1768 Clerk, trading firm of Beekman and Cruger, St. Croix
1769 Clerk, business of Nicholas Cruger, St. Croix
1772 Immigrated to Boston, Mass.
1772-1773 Attended Francis Barber's academy, Elizabethtown, N.J.
1773 Entered King's College (later Columbia University), New York, N.Y.
1774 Published
A Full Vindication of the Measures of Congress from the Calumnies of Their Enemies (New York: James Rivington. 35 pp.)
1775 Published
The Farmer Refuted: or A more impartial and comprehensive View of the Dispute between Great-Britain and the Colonies (New York: James Rivington. 78 pp.)
1776 Appointed captain in command of a provincial company of artillery
1777 Appointed aide-de-camp to George Washington with rank of lieutenant colonel
1780 Married Elizabeth Schuyler
1781 Resigned as aide-de-camp to George Washington (April 30) Given command of New York and Connecticut light infantry battalion and ordered to Virginia (July) Retired from active military duty (November)
1782 Appointed receiver of continental taxes for New York Chosen delegate from New York to the Continental Congress Admitted to practice of law as attorney and counselor before the New York Supreme Court of Judicature
1783 Resigned from Continental Congress in July Opened law office, New York, N.Y.
1784 Organizer, Bank of New York
1786 Chosen delegate to Annapolis, Md., Convention Elected, New York state assembly
1787 Named delegate to the Constitutional Convention, Philadelphia, Pa. Began series of Federalist essays
1788 Elected delegate to the New York ratifying convention
1789 Appointed secretary of the treasury
1790-1791 Prepared four major economic reports for Congress
1791 Elected member, American Philosophical Society
1795 Resigned from office of secretary of the treasury (January 31) Defended carriage tax case before United States Supreme Court
1795-1796 Wrote series of articles under the pseudonyms Philo Camillus and Camillus
1798 Appointed inspector general of the army with rank of major general
1800 Resigned as inspector general
1801 Founder, New York Evening Post
1804, July 12 Died, New York, N.Y., following duel with Aaron Burr
Scope and Content Note
The papers of Alexander Hamilton cover the years 1708 to 1903, with the bulk of material dating from 1777 to 1804. The collection is arranged in eight series: General Correspondence, Speeches and Writings, Legal Papers, Financial Papers, Family Papers, Miscellany, 1998 Addition, and Oversize.
The General Correspondence and Speeches and Writings series encompass all phases of Hamilton's public career and include several letterbook copies of letters either composed by Hamilton or in his handwriting from the time of his employment with Nicholas Cruger in St. Croix. Hamilton's public service began with his appointment as aide-de-camp to George Washington during the Revolutionary War, and numerous letters representative of the scope of his military responsibilities are found in the papers. In the period following Hamilton's resignation from active military duty, the correspondence and writings underscore his ideas concerning the form and functions of government, culminating in his participation in the Constitutional Convention and in his efforts to secure the acceptance of the new Constitution by New York's ratifying convention. However, only a fragment of one of the "Continentalist" articles and none of his Federalist essays are included in the papers.
As secretary of the treasury, Hamilton's immediate task was to establish a sound financial structure for the new government and to devise a plan for the payment of foreign, domestic, and state debts. The Speeches and Writings series contains drafts of four major economic reports submitted by Hamilton to Congress on public credit, the creation of a national bank, the establishment of a mint, and the development of a manufacturing industry. Several documents assembled in the preparation of these reports and papers relating to the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures are located in the General Correspondence and Miscellany series. In the area of foreign affairs, the relationship of the United States with France and commercial ties with Great Britain were matters of vital concern to the country. Hamilton's view of these issues is related in his correspondence, especially with George Washington, and in the series of newspaper articles published under such pseudonyms as Pacificus, No Jacobin, Philo Camillus, and Camillus.
Hamilton pursued his interest in public affairs after he resigned from the Treasury Department. He continued to advise the president and cabinet members on policy matters and drafted several of Washington's addresses to Congress, including the Farewell Address. The growing threat of war with France prompted Hamilton to write a series of articles in 1797 and 1798 presenting his analysis of the political situation which led the government to consider the status of its army. By a statute passed on 16 July 1798, Congress authorized the raising of twelve additional regiments. John Adams named Washington as commander-in-chief, and Hamilton was appointed inspector general. In this office, Hamilton had most of the responsibility for recruiting and organizing the army. Correspondence and papers between July 1798 and July 1800 constitute approximately half of the documents in the collection. Although many of the papers show Hamilton's involvement in the routine operations of the army, his correspondence, much of it with James McHenry, detail the problems inherent in recruiting and organizing regiments, supply logistics, and conditions at the forts, particularly in the western regions of the country. Copies of training manuals prepared under Hamilton's direction are in the military papers in the Miscellany series, and those drafted by him are in the Speeches and Writings series.
Hamilton began his career as an attorney in 1782, and his legal papers reflect the varied range of his practice. His cases can be generally grouped into several broad categories: those growing out of the Revolutionary War involving trespass, confiscation, and citation acts, commercial transactions, maritime insurance claims, admiralty jurisdiction, disputes pertaining to colonial land patents and western lands, questions of public law and procedure, some constitutional issues, and conflict of laws. Some of the landmark cases included in his papers are Rutgers v. Waddington, People v. Croswell, Hylton v. United States, and cases forming the LeGuen v. Gouverneur and Kemble litigation.
The Financial Papers, which form the smallest segment of the collection, consist of two volumes of accounts relating to his law practice and a folder of miscellaneous receipts. Some of the receipts are for money given to William Pearce between September 1791 and July 1792 on behalf of the Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures.
The Family Papers series includes letters and other correspondence and documents involving members of the family other than Hamilton. The series contains letters from Angelica Church and Philip John Schuyler to Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton; from Philip John Schuyler to his grandson, Philip Hamilton; and from Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton to her sister, Catherine Cochran, and to her son, Philip Hamilton. Through the marriage of Philip Hamilton to Rebecca McLane, several McLane family letters were incorporated into the papers. Most of the nonfamily correspondence of Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton relates to the management of her properties and to arrangements for the publication of Hamilton's papers. Scattered letters addressed to Alexander Hamilton (the grandson), James A. Hamilton, John Church Hamilton, and to members of the McLane family are also included in the family papers.
The Oversize series contains correspondence, reports, annotated drafts of the Constitution, writings, deeds, agreements, contracts, financial papers, certificates, and printed matter. These items were microfilmed in their original location before removal to this series.
Among the many correspondents in the papers are John Adams, Henry Clay, Elizabeth Schuyler Hamilton, John Francis Hamtramck, William Heth, John Jay, Thomas Jefferson, Rufus King, Marie Joseph Paul Yves Roch Gilbert Du Motier, Marquis de Lafayette, Henry Lee (1756-1818), Pierre Charles L'Enfant, James McHenry, James Monroe, Robert Morris, Timothy Pickering, Charles Cotesworth Pinckney, Nathan Rice, John Jacob Ulrich Rivardi, Philip John Schuyler, Theodore Sedgwick (1746-1813), William Seton, William Stephens Smith, Friedrich Wilhelm Ludolf Gerhard Augustin, Baron von Steuben, Caleb Swan, Louis de Tousard, Robert Troup, Jeremiah Wadsworth, George Washington, James Wilkinson, and Oliver Wolcott (1760-1833). A letter from Nicholas Everton to Hamilton in 1799 concerning legal matters was added to the papers in 1998.
In 1961 Columbia University Press began publication of an edition of the Papers of Alexander Hamilton, edited by Harold C. Syrett. Similarly, Columbia University Law School began publication of Hamilton's legal papers in 1964, with Julius Goebel as editor. These two editions have been used as definitive sources in the verification of names and in the dating and identification of manuscripts in the Hamilton Papers at the Library of Congress.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in eight series:
General Correspondence, 1734-1804, n.d.
Speeches and Writings File, 1778-1804, n.d.
Legal File, 1708-1804, n.d.
Financial Papers, 1782-1804, n.d.
Family Papers, 1737-1903, n.d.
Miscellany, 1711-1820, n.d.
1998 Addition, 1780-1799
Oversize, 1775-1805, n.d.
Container List
- General Correspondence, 1734-1804, n.d. (Box 1-23, Reel 1-21)
  Letters received; draft, recipient copies, and transcripts of letters sent; and attachments.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - 11 July 1734-21 Dec. 1781, (6 folders) (Box 1, Reel 1)
  - 8 Jan. 1782-28 Dec. 1786, (7 folders) (Box 2, Reel 1-2)
  - 8 Feb. 1787-31 Dec. 1790, (6 folders) (Box 3, Reel 2-3)
  - 3 Jan. 1791-27 Mar. 1792, (6 folders) (Box 4, Reel 3-4)
  - 4 Apr. 1792-27 June 1793, (6 folders) (Box 5, Reel 4-5)
  - 2 July 1793-26 Feb. 1795*, *A letter dated 1 May 1794 may be found on reel 4 following the date 8 Sept. 1792; (7 folders) (Box 6, Reel 5-6)
  - 9 Mar. 1795-31 Dec. 1796, (7 folders) (Box 7, Reel 6-7)
  - 1 Jan. 1797-30 Aug. 1798, (7 folders) (Box 8, Reel 7-8)
  - 1 Sept. 1798-28 Feb. 1799, (7 folders) (Box 9, Reel 8-9)
  - 1 Mar.-18 Apr. 1799, (6 folders) (Box 10, Reel 9)
  - 19 Apr.-27 May 1799, (6 folders) (Box 11, Reel 10)
  - 28 May-7 July 1799, (7 folders) (Box 12, Reel 11)
  - 8 July-14 Aug. 1799, (6 folders) (Box 13, Reel 12)
  - 15 Aug.-14 Sept. 1799, (6 folders) (Box 14, Reel 12-13)
  - 15 Sept.-5 Oct. 1799, (6 folders) (Box 15, Reel 13-14)
  - 6-31 Oct. 1799, (6 folders) (Box 16, Reel 14-15)
  - 1 Nov.-5 Dec. 1799, (7 folders) (Box 17, Reel 15-16)
  - 6 Dec. 1799-19 Jan. 1800, (7 folders) (Box 18, Reel 16-17)
  - 20 Jan.-10 Mar. 1800, (6 folders) (Box 19, Reel 17)
  - 11 Mar.-14 Apr. 1800, (7 folders) (Box 20, Reel 18)
  - 15 Apr.-18 May 1800, (6 folders) (Box 21, Reel 18-19)
  - 19 May 1800-24 Mar. 1801, (7 folders) (Box 22, Reel 19-20)
  - 17 Apr. 1801-10 July 1804, n.d., (5 folders) (Box 23, Reel 20-21)
- Speeches and Writings File, 1778-1804, n.d. (Box 23-26, Reel 21-23)
  Drafts and copies of speeches, articles, notes, reports, and miscellaneous writings.
  Arranged chronologically. Poems and undated and miscellaneous writings are located at the end of the series.
  - 1778, 24 Dec., "Narrative of an Affair of Honor between General [Charles] Lee and Colonel [John] Laurens" (Box 23, Reel 20-21)
  - [1782, 18 Apr.], "The Continentalist, No. V," incomplete
  - 1783
    - [18 June], "Report on a Military Peace Establishment"
    - July, defense of Congress
    - [July], unsubmitted resolution calling for a convention to amend the Articles of Confederation
  - [1784, 23 Feb.-15 Mar.], constitution and outline of a charter for the Bank of New York
  - [1786, Dec.], "Notes on the History of North and South America"
  - 1787
    - New York Assembly
      - [9 Feb. ], An Act for Raising certain Yearly Taxes within this State, outline and three drafts
      - [14 Mar.]
        - An Act Acknowledging the Independence of Vermont, draft
      - Remarks on an Act Acknowledging the Independence of Vermont
    - Constitutional Convention
      - [1-26 June], notes taken in the convention
      - [18 June]
        - "Plan of Government"
        - "Notes for Speech in the Convention proposing a Plan of Government"
      - [17 Sept.], draft of a constitution, facsimile copies
      - [17-30 Sept.], "Conjectures about the New Constitution"
  - 1788
    - [Jan.-Feb.], An Act to Incorporate the Freeholders and Inhabitants of the Town of Marbletown
    - New York ratifying convention
      - [20, 24 June], notes on debates
      - [27 June], notes on a speech by Melancton Smith
      - [12, 17 July], notes for speeches
  - [1789, 4 July], "Eulogium on the late Major-General [Nathanael] Greene"
  - 1790
    - [9 Jan.]
      - An Act Imposing Certain Inland Duties on Foreign Wines
      - "Report Relative to a Provision for the Support of Public Credit"
    - [5 Aug.], "Report on Additional Sums Necessary for the Support of the Government"
    - [1 Dec.], "Notes of Objects for Consideration of the President"
    - [13 Dec.] (Box 24, Reel 21)
      - "First Report on the Further Provision Necessary for Establishing Public Credit," first and second drafts, (2 folders)
      - "Second Report on the Further Provision Necessary for Establishing Public Credit (Report on a National Bank)"
    - [Dec.], An Act to Incorporate the Bank of the United States
  - 1791
    - [28 Jan.], "Report on the Establishment of a Mint," with second drafts and notes, (3 folders)
    - [23 Feb.], "Report on the Constitutionality of a National Bank," draft and two copies
    - [Aug.], Society for Establishing Useful Manufactures prospectus
    - [5 Dec.], "Report on the Subject of Manufactures," first, second, third, and fourth drafts and outline, (4 folders)
  - 1792
    - [23 Jan.], "Report on Public Debt and Loans," first and second drafts and an abstract
    - [1-4 Mar.], notes on Thomas Jefferson's "Report of Instructions for the Commissioners to Spain"
    - [May-Aug.], "The Vindication"
    - [4, 11, Aug.], "An American, Nos. I-II"
    - [19 Aug.], "Anti-Defamer"
    - [11 Sept.], "Civis to Mercator"
    - [15-31 Oct.], draft of George Washington's fourth annual address to Congress
    - [30 Oct.-17 Nov.], "A Plain Honest Man"
  - [1792-1793], "View of the Commercial Regulations of France and Great Britain in Reference to the United States"
  - [1792-1795], "The Defence, No. I"
  - 1793
    - "Idea Concerning a Lottery"
    - "On James Blanchard," includes document dated 8 Jan. 1793 used as part of the evidence
    - [13-15 Mar.], "Observer"
    - [Apr.], statement on remarks by John F. Mercer
    - [14-16 May], "On the Reception of Edmond Charles Genet in Philadelphia"
    - [15 May], "Opinion respecting prizes taken by privateers fitted out at Charleston"
    - [May], "Defense of the President's Neutrality Proclamation"
    - [29 June-27 July], "Pacificus, Nos. I-VII"
    - [8 July], case of the Little Sarah (brigantine), outline and reasons, with Thomas Jefferson's opinion attached (Box 25, Reel 22)
    - [18 July], draft of questions submitted to the justices of the Supreme Court
    - [29-30 July], proposed rules concerning the arming and equipping of vessels by belligerents in the ports of the United States
    - [31 July-8 Aug.], "No Jacobin, Nos. I-III"
    - [2-16 Aug.], notes for a letter to Gouverneur Morris
    - [3 Aug.], opinion on fitting out of privateers in the ports of the United States
    - [5 Aug.], "Philo Pacificus"
    - [Nov.], draft for George Washington's fifth annual message to Congress, incomplete
    - List of French distressed persons
    - "On the Rise of a War Party," incomplete
  - 1794
    - [6-13 Jan.], proposed presidential message to Congress concerning revocation of Edmond Charles Genet's diplomatic status
    - [31 Jan.-7 Feb.], "Americus, Nos. I-II"
    - [Mar.-May], draft of a proposed message from George Washington to Congress
    - [23 Apr.], points to be considered in the instructions to John Jay
    - [Apr.-May], suggestions for a commercial treaty
    - [19 May], "List of Names From Whence To Take A Minister for France"
    - [Aug.], note on the funding system
    - [Dec.], "Measures in the War Department Which It May Be Expedient To Adopt"
    - "The Cause of France"
    - "The French Revolution"
  - 1795
    - [1 Jan.], draft of a proclamation by George Washington, with copy
    - [ca. 16 Jan.], notes for the "Report on a Plan for the Further Support of Public Credit"
    - [9-11 July], "Remarks on the Treaty of Amity, Commerce, and Navigation lately made between the United States and Great Britain"
    - [25 July-9 Jan. 1796], "The Defence, Nos. II-XXXVIII," by Camillus, (2 folders)
    - [July], "The Defence of the Funding System," with notes
    - [July], "Horatius, No. II"
    - [Aug.], notes on objections to the British treaty
    - [11 Nov.], "Explanation"
    - [28 Nov.-7 Dec.], draft of George Washington's seventh annual address to Congress
  - [1795-1796]
    - "American Jacobins"
    - "Relations With France"
  - 1796 (Box 26, Reel 22-23)
    - [29 Mar.], draft of George Washington's reply to the resolution introduced into the House of Representatives by Edward Livingston on 2 Mar. 1796
    - [22 Apr.], "To the Citizens Who Shall be Convened This Day in the Fields in the City of New York"
    - [May], design for a seal for the United States
    - [30 July], draft of George Washington's Farewell Address, with facsimile, and "Abstract of Points To Form an Address"
    - [Sept.-Dec.], "The War in Europe"
    - [10 Nov.], draft of George Washington's eighth annual address to Congress
  - 1797
    - [27 Jan.-27 Mar.], "The Warning," by Americus
    - [25 Aug.], draft of the "Reynolds Pamphlet"
  - 1798
    - [Apr.], "A French Faction"
    - [16-19 Apr.], "The Stand, Nos. V-VI"
    - [22 May], "For The Time Piece"
    - [13 June], "The Detector"
    - [5-15 July], "Plan for a Legion," with copy
  - [Dec. 1799-Mar. 1800]
    - "Plan of the Formation of a Regiment for Exercise or Battle"
    - "Formation and Disposition of a Regiment of Infantry"
  - [1799], "Elements of the Tactics of the Infantry"
  - 1800
    - [Mar.], An Act for Better Organizing the Corps of Artillerists and Engineers
    - [9 Mar.], An Act for Establishing an Academy for Instruction Relative to the Military and Naval Service of the United States
    - [24 Oct.], "Letter from Alexander Hamilton, Concerning the Public Conduct and Character of John Adams, Esq., President of the United States," incomplete
    - "Rules for Philip Hamilton"
  - [10 Feb. 1804], speech at a meeting of Federalists in Albany, N.Y.
  - Miscellaneous
  - Poems
  - Undated
- Legal File, 1708-1804, n.d. (Box 26-35, Reel 22-29)